Welcome to the session 2. As I already said, this course is designed for everyone, like
firstures, as well as who are working as a different domain information technology, the
IT, maybe the sales are programming. So, the person they will be very interested in cyber
security, but they didn't get a chance to our lander, ok. So, we designed that course,
they send a course in this day, anyone who is jumping to the cyber security or who is
a fresher or more enthusiast to learn the cyber security things, this course will be very
suitable for everyone, ok. So, sir basics. So, the key foundation of the ethical hacking
and cyber security, it will start with the networking. So, why we are networking? Many
of something in why we need networking in cyber security and the offense and defense
error, what is the reason for that. So, if you see that in the networking, there will
be the data communication from one machine to another, ok. So, if there is no data communication,
no need of security, no need to secure any data, there is no attack or no hacker or no
malware will be there, right. So, sake power as a foundational, so, we need some networking
knowledge. This session is not designed for our networking professionals who will be
more, more interested in networking, but this session will teach what are the things and
what are the knowledge and skills you need for a drive, drive into ethical hacking and
the cyber security, this session will be key part of the whole course, ok. So, if you
are professional in this session, you can understand anything in cyber security, anything
anything in the hacking, the upcoming sections, ok. So, let us begin with the networking
for offense and a different side, let us discuss in the first topic called the OSI model.
So, many of them, maybe many of them here in your college and schools, the OSI, OSI stand
for open system interconnections. So, this was introduced by the ISO in 1984. So, this OSI
has seven layers basically, this seven layers represents, this seven layers are responsible
for how the data comes transmitting from one machine to another, ok. So, maybe some of
something I am using Mac OS, then what is a what is a representation of the layer.
So, if you are using Mac, if you are using Linux, if you are using Windows, Android, any
operating system around the world or if you are going to develop a new operating system,
no problem, this layer will be the key part of data transmission from one machine to another.
For all the architecture, 32-bit as well as a 64-bit, for all architecture, this OSI model
will be the basic responsible for data communication from one machine to another, ok.
So, let us draw some diagram to understand the OSI model, ok. So, let us think of it, there
is one machine and this is U and here you can see another machine. So, this is your bank
server, ok. Let us take an example, this is a any server, let us take an example of a bank
server, ok. So, let us first start with the how much layer there is, there is a seven layers
I already discussed. So, let us start with the application layer, so our first layer will
be a application layer, right. So, what is an application? So, if you are seeing any applications
like, for example, you can take an Instagram of application and sorry, and the Canva that
is one of the application and some browser applications like Firefox, MSS, Pira, Safari, and
Chrome, these are some browser applications, right. So, if you want to communicate with
your bank server, so what you need, right. So, I have a Google Chrome, I was giving some
STFC in Google Chrome, right. So, I need to, if I want to communicate to my bank, so I am
going to Google and I am typing the STFC, and I am communicating with the bank, I am seeing
what are the transactions and out there and what are the transaction history, everything,
right. I am using my browser application. So, the application in the service like Chrome,
it is Firefox, so whatever you can say any application, right. You can consider any application
or what you have, okay. So, not only the application, this application layer will
give you some protocols. What is a protocol? The protocol is like a rule, okay. So, if I
am typing a Google, I just type Google Drive. So, if you see the protocol, there is a
one of the, one of some protocols we have added, right. So, that is a HD TPS, maybe some,
some, many of them learned this HD TPS and HD TPS. So, HD TPS like a hypertext transport
protocol, and HD TPS is like a hypertext transport protocol security. So, there are two
protocols in the web application when you are communicating to any servers or any application,
any servers across the world. So, the protocols will become here, okay. The HD TPS, not only
the browser based protocols, there is a lot of application, right. Outlook, maybe example
of Outlook, that all the applications will become under the application layer, okay.
Outlook, Zoom, if you are going for Teams, everything will be coming, coming up in the application
layer. The protocol is also like, you can say it as FTP, there is a lot of protocols,
you can discuss in, discuss all the protocols, common ports and protocols in the upcoming
sessions, but now we can explore the OSM model properly, okay. So, as I already said, this
was an important video for everyone who is a fresher for landing the OSM, okay. The next
layer will be the presentation layer, right. So, you can see the next layer, it was a presentation
layer. So, what is a presentation layer? So, I am presenting something that is not a presentation
layer. So, what is a presentation? The presentation layer is responsible for a few things.
So, almost a compression, another another encryption, okay. So, this layer is responsible
for this both. So, let us think why we need a compression and why we need a encryption.
So, let us understand what is a compression. So, many of them used to be in rare or
zomency or any type tools. So, you are covering some files and you are under giving the
files. So, the compression is like, if you want to transfer a data from one machine to another
like, let us take an example. This machine needs to send 100 gigabytes of data to this
computer, okay, to this computer. This is you. And so, your network bandwidth speed was,
your network connection speed was like, network speed, I will give NS like, it is like
10 GV per seconds, okay. It is like 10 GV per second, okay. And if you are transferring
this 100 GB to this machine, how much seconds it will take, maybe it will take some 10
seconds, right. It is the data communication speed was like, GBPS, 10 GBPS per second, it
will take some 10 seconds to transfer the data to this machine, but it is not possible.
So, 10 GBPS, it is not possible for network communication, but let us, I just say with an
example, okay. So, if you come to this 100 GB, if you convert this 100 GB into 50 GB, now,
this 50 GB needs to transfer this computer, right. So, it will only take 5 seconds, right.
So, absolutely, you can able to transfer the data quickly and it will be very fast when
you are transferring the data, right. It will be less the time within a lesser time, we
can able to transfer all the data, right. So, we have a compression here and what is
the encryption? So, let us take a live example, what is the encryption? So, encryption
is like converting your data into the plain text, PT, I will give PT plain text to
cipher text, okay. So, what is the plain text and this cipher text, what is the different
let us, take a quick example. So, what is that? I will go for some online encryption
tools. So, I just using the encrypt text online. So, I am giving high here and the encryption
algorithm was AES. So, AES like stand for advanced encryption standard and you need to give
the key, okay. So, I am giving the T, Y, U, I, okay. This is a key I am giving and I just
clicked on the encrypt the data. So, you can see the data how it was encryptor. So, this
is called as the cipher text, okay. This is the plain text and this is the cipher text,
this is the key which used to encrypt this high, okay. So, in the representation layer,
the encryption will be one of the method, one of the security mechanism for our data,
okay. So, why we need a security, in this way we need an encryption and why we need a security,
okay. Let us think of it, there is a, so, you are here and your data will be gone to one
of the service provider like DSLL or Word of Phone or Aircell or any Internet service provider
and it will go to the tabar or some location or it will go into the underground cables,
okay, and it going to the receiver, right. So, these are the, these are the ways your data
was transmitting from U to U, your bank server, right. So, what if someone, some attacker,
sitting here, okay, attacker, sitting in the service provider room and he is watching all
your data, what you are sending, okay. If it was a plain text, if you are sending high to here,
if it is a plain text, he can able to watch what you are sending, right. So, he can able to easily
capture all your data, what if you can, you can just send high, that is not a problem,
but if you are using the bank application, you are sending the user names and passwords, right.
If the attacker got a user names and passwords, he can easily steal all your money, it is a security
problem, right. So, we have an encryption here, so if there is encryption, so you need to decrypt
the data, right. So, the decryption is sort of simple mechanism, so you can, we can copy this same
cipher text and we can go for a decryption, this is the key we have given and let us go to the decryption
and we can paste the key here, T, Y, U, I, this is a key which is key we have provided and I just
giving the decryption, so now you can see it was giving a high to me, right. So, this is the
plain text I have encrypted with the cipher text. Now, I just gave the cipher text and decrypted
the data to the plain text, okay. This is the encryption and the decryption, okay. So, if you are
sending the encrypted data here something, some random U, I, X, W, I, X, Z, I, J, some random
X data here that attacker unable to know what you are sending, right. So, this is the encryption
and decryption and security mechanism in a OSM model, okay. So, let us discuss about the third layer,
so third layer is like a session layer, okay session. So, in a session layer, let us think of it,
there is a plain and there is a server, so now you have a bank server and you have a copy
and U. So, if you want to communicate with the bank server, so you need a session layer,
session layer is responsible for initiating the session, communication, okay,
initiating the communication, okay, and terminating your connection. It is responsible for
terminating as well as initiating, okay. So, if you want to communicate with Google,
I can just give Google.com, okay. My session layer will responsible for communicating with the
Google.com. So, once I research everything with Google, so what I can do, I can easily
close it off. So, now the session layer will terminate my session, okay.
This will establish a connection as well as it will terminate a connection. So, once you
research everything, it will use some sort of APIs, so we can discuss it later,
so what is an API stand for application programming interface. So, we can discuss it later,
the APIs, okay. So, the next layer will be the transport layer. So, what is a transport?
So, the transport is used for going to unplace to another or traveling from one place to another,
so in OSIM model the transport layer has a same meaning. In the transport layer there will be
a two protocols, one is a TCP and another one is a UDP, okay. So, the TCP stands for a transmission
controlled protocol and UDP stands for user data gram protocol, okay. So, we can say
the TCP is a connection oriented, okay. This is a very important point connection oriented.
And the UDP we can state as a connectionless,
okay. So, I just explaining what TCP and UDP will do here, but I will provide a detail explanation
in next video of TCP, okay. There will be a three-hand signal, we can discuss it
later in the next video itself, okay. So, why we are saying it's a connection oriented, okay.
So, if you are sending some text messages or voice messages to your colleague or your
friends in WhatsApp or any chatting platforms, so the data will not be lost, right. The data will
be sent to your friend or they can give a sequence to your data, all the data will be transmitted
successfully. No missing if you are giving high, how are you buddy? So, every high, how are you buddy?
Every text, every words will be properly received to your friend from you, right. So, there will
be no words or miss, there is no text words or there is no characters or missed here, okay.
So, what are the things you are sending? You can, we can make an assurance, every data will be
transferred to your receiver or your friend, anyone, okay. But UDP, you can take a message as
normal connection. So, you are giving the username, password,
or you are giving some text message to your friends or anyone, okay. What is the connection list?
So, we can take a basic example of an IMO video card, okay.
So, if you are calling your friend, so you are communicating with your friends in a video call,
sometime, your connection was some, uh, interrupted, your connection was like slow. So, now,
you are unable to retrieve what you said, right. So, sometime your connection will be slow,
you said something and your friend can't able to hear what you said, so you were asking
one more time, what you said and all, okay. So, there was a connection list, okay.
We can't able to give assurance to the data what you sent, there was a connection list.
So, these are most of the time the UDP was used by the video cards and all, because the data
transferred need to be very faster, uh, TCP was not fast, like UDP, UDP was very fast, then TCP,
because there is no, um, handshakes and checksums are there, uh, so that it will be very faster.
In the video calls and, uh, the audio calls, we need the UDP because the data communication
needs to be very fast, so that we are using UDP in the, uh, data communications, okay.
So, the video calls and all we are using the, uh, UDP based, uh, so I just give some examples what
happened here, uh, there was not exactly, but this is the exact example what the TCP and UDP,
like TCP is like a connection oriented and UDP is like a connection list, okay. So, this is an
example I am a video call, you can't able to, uh, give assurance to your data what you, what you
do transferred, okay. So, the next layer will be the network layer, right. So, what is the network
layer? So, let us think of it. So, you are here and you need to send some data to your bank
server, okay. So, what you will do? So, you need to know the address of the bank server,
right. So, every home has an address, even my home has an address, every, uh, everybody
home has an address. So, if you ask, if you want to send one parcel to, uh, your friend or your
colleague's home, so what you will do, you will, uh, send it through the post, send it to the
courier, right. It will be, uh, giving the address from address to address and all, right.
So, in the same way, if there is a bank server or any servers like Google or Facebook or anything,
the server has a address, okay. So, if you are, let me show the address of the google.com.
So, this is the, uh, IP address of google.com, 142.
So, you need to know what was the address of the bank, right. So, if you want to send some data to
the bank server, so you need to know what's address of the bank server, right. So, that the
address will be the IP address. In the network layer, the source, IP, source IP is your,
your IP, what's my IP, right. So, you can see my IP address, uh, 192.168.18.
Uh, 29, 192.168.18.29, okay. This is my source IP. And, uh, what's the destination IP?
So, the destination IP will be the bank server, right. Let's think and example, your bank
server IP is, uh, 157.168. Uh, 18.5. This is our bank server IP, okay. So, in the network layers,
source IP and the destination IP will be added, okay. So, the next, let's come to another layer.
Next layer will be the data link layer.
So, in data link layer, there's one more address we need to add, okay. So, we need to add a MAC address.
So, MAC address is a unique address for every machine, see every IoT device or uh,
your smart, smart features or your mobile phones, uh, next, uh, multi, every IoT device and
your, uh, email based device, it has a MAC ID, like the MAC ID will be E9 and F8, like this will be
the MAC address, okay. We will discuss the MAC address in the next, uh, in the later, uh, sessions.
Uh, it will be a little bit topic, it will be confusing if I discussed it now, okay.
So, this MAC address will be added here, okay. So, the next layer will be the physical layer.
So, what is the physical layer? So, physical layer is responsible for
transforming our data to own machine to another, okay. So, here you can see the data.
This is your data and this data to be converted into 0s and 0s and 1s, right. We have seen it,
the data need to travel, uh, through the cable, uh, right. So, it will be transferred, uh,
it will be converted to 0s and 1s. The physical layer is responsible for that. So, the routers,
everything will be in the physical layers, okay. It will need to route your packets to, uh,
from your side, from you to your bank server, right. So, uh, it will convert the 0s, 0s and bits,
data into bits, okay, 0s and 1. And it will convert the data from your machine to the bank bank server,
okay. So, this, uh, little overview of the OSA model. So, let me discuss, uh, some
in-depth concept. Let's think of it. There's an application layer. So, in the application layer,
your data will be like, there's a data, okay. So, your data will be like, uh, high,
okay. So, the next few coming to the presentation layer,
so in the presentation layer. So, your data will be like,
some encrypted format, E, Y, X, is it, okay. We already discussed about the blank text
text on that. And again, we have a session layer. So, again, your data will be like, data
with, uh, encrypted text, the same. So, next,
we'll just, uh, your data, your data is coming to the transport layer. So, in the transport layer,
there's one thing to discuss. Your data can be segmented, okay. Some time,
so you need to transfer 100 GB data to your, uh, colleague or one of your friend, uh, server.
So, the 100 GB data will be converted into segments, okay. 10 GB. 10 GB, based on your internet
connections, based on the connection, it will be segmented into packets, okay. Sorry,
segments, okay. The data will be, uh, segmented, okay. Different different segments,
okay. 10 GB, 10 GB, 10 GB, okay. It will be segmented, okay. Now, your data,
and EX, let's, uh, we'll segment this one, okay.
And EX, is it, okay. There's no data, I have a data, uh, or a segmented. And it was using some
RTCP, right. Next, we can call this as a segment, okay. Because our data is segmented into two parts,
okay. Next, let's come into the network layer. So, in network layer, I'll be already discussed,
there is an IP address and, uh, source IP and destination IP will be heard. So, now,
source IP, the protocol is a TCP and EX, okay. This will be there, okay.
So, for EX, there is a TCP, source IP destination IP. For EX, it's set, there is, uh,
integration separate, uh, packet TCP, source IP destination IP, okay. It, it, it divided into two parts,
okay. Now, we will call this as, uh, packet, okay. Pack it one,
and packet two. So, now, let's, physical layer, the final layer, sorry,
uh, in between, there is a data link, right? Uh, I forgot that data link.
So, in the data link layer, we already discussed, there's, one more thing will be added,
force, MAC and destination MAC. This two things will be added here in your data and with the TCP,
force IP, destination IP, okay. For packet one, and same for packet two, okay. So, another layer was
physical layer. So, in the physical layer, this data will be transferred to 0, 1, 0, 1,
0, and 1, okay. So, the, the 0, 1 will be communicated through our cable and it will win to the,
go to the, your bank server, right. This is the entire data communication, okay. So, we have,
uh, some more things to discuss. We will discuss that in the upcoming sections. We need to
discuss the error checksum, uh, how the TCP was, uh, handling the, uh, missing packets,
how we can say the TCP was more labeled than the UDP in the later session. So, now, I hope
everything everyone will have a clear understanding about, uh, the OSM model. So, someone have a doubt,
I know maybe, uh, you have a doubt. So, we can solve that, uh, doubts in the upcoming sessions,
okay. So, the upcoming section will give you more clear understanding about all the protocols
and what are the in-depth concepts in networking, okay. So, thanks for watching and let's
see you on the next video, TCP, uh, the brief explanation, okay. Thank you. Bye-bye.